Finding Aid for Stefan Florescu Papers 1946-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Stefan Florescu Papers 1946-2002, 1965-1985
Florescu, Stefan.
2 linear feet
Stefan Florescu, a quadriplegic, was involved in activities and organizations for the handicapped in the Detroit area and was founder of Michigan Wheelchair Athletic Committee. The collection includes personal/biographical material, files relating to his organizational activities, and files pertaining to wheelchair athletics.
0180 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Stefan Florescu (Donor no. 9108 ), July 2001.
The collection is open for research.
Stefan Florescu was born on December 26, 1926 to a family of Romanian descent. He grew up in Davenport Iowa, attending St. Ambrose High School and one year at Saint Ambrose College, where he was a track and field star. From 1945 to 1947, Florescu served in World War II in Korea. When discharged, Florescu returned to St. Ambrose College and graduated in 1952 with a degree in sociology and teaching. Florescu had lined up a teaching job for the fall, but that summer, Florescu had an accident that changed his life. Diving from a pier, he broke his neck between the sixth and seventh cervical vertebrae. Florescu was now a quadriplegic. His recovery from the accident took two long years and the special care of a veteran's hospital, for at the time hospitals were not well equipped to handle quadriplegics.
As a quadriplegic Florescu's life changed completely. After his rehabilitation he became very involved in activities and organizations for the handicapped in the Detroit area. Florescu founded the Michigan Paralyzed Veterans of America (PVA) chapter and became a member of the National Association for the Physically Handicapped (NAPH). In 1961 Florescu was the first quadriplegic to attend the National Wheelchair Games, where he competed with paraplegics, although he continually came in last because of his greater disability. Because of Florescu's attempts at competition, the National Wheelchair Games eventually developed categories of physical limitation so those handicapped could compete against others of the same abilities. In 1964 Florescu founded the Michigan Wheelchair Athletic Committee and in 1965, the first Michigan Wheelchair Games were held. Florescu continually participated in the games in races, swimming, and table tennis and became known as "Captain Wheels". In 1975 he was included in the Wheelchair Athletics Hall of Fame, and 1983 Florescu was entered into the St. Ambrose College Athletic Hall of Fame. As of the year 2000, Florescu has been involved in 40 consecutive years in wheelchair sports, with 39 consecutive years in national competition.
Florescu took a very active role in several disabled rights organizations, serving as the National Sports Director for the PVA from 1962-1965, and as the National President of the NAPH from 1966-1968. Florescu is an active writer and editor in the organization's newsletters and has constantly participated in many activities. Florescu worked with the Downriver Handicapped League and founded the Rolling Romanians, a sports club to support local wheelchair athletics. In the early 1970's, Florescu became a founder of the Detroit Architectural Barriers Committee, to encourage handicapped access to all buildings, the first such committee in the US. Because many communities in the Detroit area were not complying with federal regulation creating wheelchair access to public buildings and designated handicapped parking spaces, the committee and others brought suit against the communities to install access in 1981.
Florescu is very proud and loyal to his Romanian heritage, starting a Romanian Literature program in 1982, as well as his work with the Rolling Romanians, combining his passions of wheelchair sports and Romanian tradition. Florescu has continually worked to make his community a better place, including planning a local neighborhood association for Lincoln Park in the early 1980's. Florescu, an accomplished vocalist, won a national folk music competition sponsored by the Veterans Association in 1982. After his success at the festival, Florescu locally released an album of songs to inspire the paralyzed.
Florescu continued his involvement in many organizations and committees, including the Downriver Handicapped League, the Michigan Handicappers, as well as the Michigan PVA and NAPH throughout the 1980's until today. Florescu is a man dedicated to the well being and inspiration of others and the causes of disability rights.
The Stephan Florescu Papers contain materials from 1947-2001, documenting his active life and role in the disability rights movement, particularly in wheelchair athletics and barrier free access. The collection contains information on many local, state, and national level handicapped organizations and wheelchair athletics. The papers are arranged into three series: Personal/Biographical, Organizations, and Wheelchair Athletics.
Subjects:
Architectural Barriers Committee (Detroit, Mich.); Florescu, Stefan.; Paralyzed Veterans of America. Michigan Chapter.; Physically handicapped--Michigan.; Quadriplegics--Michigan.; Wheelchair sports--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Florescu, Stefan.; Handicapped persons--Michigan.; Quadriplegics--Rehabilitation--Michigan.; Wheelchair sports--Michigan.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Personal/Biographical
  The Personal/Biographical materials consist of biographical clippings, two drafts of a biography, diaries (from his time in Korea during World War II), scrapbooks and clippings documenting his activities in the handicapped community and as a wheelchair athlete, material about his education at St. Ambrose College, and limited information about his wife, Caroline (Tupper) Florescu. A mobility study with an extensive interview provides a wealth of current information. Also contains information about Florescu's family and Romanian heritage, a Romanian Literature Program he began, materials relating to the formation of a Lincoln Park Neighborhood Association, and sheet music for his hobby of folk singing, although there is no information about the album Florescu released. This series also contains various photographs and a VHS videocassette tape of a Lincoln Park Council Meeting where several testimonials in his honor were made and Stefan Florescu was presented with a key to the city.
  - Biographical
    - Biographical Materials and Clippings, undated 1939-2000 (Box 1)
    - Korean Diaries 1947 (Box 1)
    - St. Ambrose College Scrapbook 1951 (Box 1)
    - St. Ambrose College Class Notes 1951 (Box 1)
    - St. Ambrose College Sociological Casework Notes 1951 (Box 1)
    - Teaching Certification and Civil Service Exam 1952 (Box 1)
    - Photograph Scrapbook "Rehabilitation of A Quadriplegic", circa 1953 (Box 1)
    - A Guide to the Handicapped Clubs in Detroit Area, booklet by Florescu 1966 (Box 1)
    - Scrapbook of Clippings 1972-1978 (Box 1)
    - Biography Manuscript circa 1975 (Box 1)
    - Caroline (Tupper) Florescu and Family Clippings 1980-1991 (Box 1)
    - Romanian-American Groups, Florescu extended family 1975-2000 (Box 1)
    - Biography Manuscript circa 1998 (Box 1)
    - Mobility study interview 2001 (Box 1)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 1)
    - Stefan Florescu presented with key to Lincoln Park at local council meeting videocassette, undated (Box 1)
  - Other Activities
    - Maria Alexandru, Romanian Table Tennis Player, Visit to US 1978 (Box 1)
    - Romanian Literature Program 1982 (Box 1)
    - Neighborhood Associations Clippings 1980-1984 (Box 1)
    - Lincoln Park Neighborhood Association, Lafayette Neighborhood Council 1962-1988, 2001-2002 (Box 1)
    - Sheet Music and Folk Singing, undated 1984 (Box 1)
- Organizations
  The Organizations series includes various materials from many of the handicapped organizations Florescu was involved with. The greatest amount of information is about the Michigan Architectural Barriers committee and its lawsuit against various Michigan communities. Other materials included are from the Michigan Association of Handicappers, the National Association of the Physically Handicapped (NAPH), and the Michigan Paralyzed Veterans of America (PVA). There is also a set of newsletters from the Michigan PVA in which Florescu wrote, edited or was portrayed in.
  - Architectural Barriers Committee
    - General 1975-1981 (Box 1)
    - Clippings 1981-1992 (Box 1)
    - Standards 1961; Violation Reports, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1971-1975 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1976-1981 (Box 1)
    - Bylaws, Minutes, and Financial Records 1976-1981 (Box 2)
    - Lawsuit on Handicapped Access in Detroit area 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - Marlow W. Munns Disabled Activist Clippings 1972 (Box 2)
    - Patrick Casey, Disabled Rights Attorney Obituary 1998 (Box 2)
  - Other Organizations
    - American Coalition of Citizens with Disabilities 1978 (Box 2)
    - Downriver Handicapped League Clippings 1960 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Commission on Handicapper Concerns 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Paralyzed Veterans of America (PVA) 1980-1996 (Box 2)
    - Michigan PVA Newsletters 1980-1993 (Box 2)
      scattered dates
    - Michigan PVA First President Bill Russell, Clippings 1961-1963 (Box 2)
    - National Association of the Physically Handicapped (NAPH), Metro Detroit Chapter 1962-2002 (Box 2)
    - NAPH Membership Information 1996-1997 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters of Various Disabled Rights Organizations 1960-2001 (Box 2)
  - General Information, Disability Organizations
    - Inspirational Scrapbook, "What the Handicapped are doing" 1946-1947 (Box 2)
    - Handicapped Club Guides 1966, 1979-1985 (Box 2)
    - Disability Groups Clippings 1978-1992 (Box 2)
    - Transportation Clippings 1992 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan Spinal Care Center/Michigan Independent Living 2002 (Box 2)
- Wheelchair Athletics
  The materials on Wheelchair Athletics consist of records about Florescu's 40 years of continuous involvement in sports. Included are materials about the National Wheelchair Athletic Association, the Michigan Wheelchair Athletic Committee, and the Rolling Romanians (Florescu's local sports club). The papers contain the National Wheelchair Athletics Certification, brochures from the first Michigan Games in 1965, planning materials for the 1987 Michigan wheelchair games in Ann Arbor, and the book Wheelchair Champions, by Harriet May Savitz, published in 1978 which includes Florescu's athletic accomplishments.
  - Clippings and Printed Material
    - Wheelchair Sports Clippings 1969-2002 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Wheelchair Sports Clippings 1995-2001 (Box 2)
    - National Wheelchair Athletics Wheelchair Champions, Book by Harriet May Savitz, 1978 (Box 2)
  - National Wheelchair Athletics
    - Guide and Constitution undated, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Rules and Constitution 1983 (Box 2)
    - Certification 1985 (Box 2)
    - Games 1980-1989 (Box 2)
    - Games 1990-2000 (Box 2)
    - Press Releases 1994-1998 (Box 2)
    - Walter Rumchey, Wheelchair Athlete, Hall of Fame Application 1997, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Wheelchair Athletics
    - Games 1965 (Box 2)
    - Games and planning 1987 (Box 2)
    - Rolling Romanians Sport Club 1980-1984 (Box 2)